GRAEME MACGILCHRIST

University College, Oxford, OX1 4BH graeme.macgilchrist@univ.ox.ac.uk (+44) 7908568289 gmacgilchrist.github.io

Research interests

I have broad research interests within high-latitude physical oceanography and the interaction between the ocean circulation and other components of the climate system. My PhD work has focussed on ocean ventilation, particularly on the mechanisms and variability of deep ocean ventilation in the North Atlantic, the impact of mesoscale variability on ventilation pathways, and the role of ventilation in the uptake of carbon in the Southern Ocean.

Education

DPhil Physical Oceanography University of Oxford, U.K. Thesis: Lagrangian perspectives on ocean ventilation Supervisors: Prof. David Marshall and Dr. Helen Johnson MSc Oceanography (with Distinction) University of Southampton, U.K. Dissertation: Quantifying carbon sequestration in the Arctic Ocean (84%) Supervisor: Prof. Alberto Naveira Garabato MMath Mathematics (Hons, 1st Class) Newcastle University, U.K. Broad degree incorporating applied maths, pure maths and statistics

Publications

MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (in prep) Characteristics and variability of deep North Atlantic ocean ventilation in an eddy-permitting numerical ocean circulation model, to be submitted to *Journal of Climate*.

Dissertation: Magnetic fields in accretion discs (78%)

- MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (in prep) Reframing the polar Southern Ocean carbon cycle, to be submitted to *Nature Geoscience*.
- van Sebille, E. et al. (2018) Lagrangian ocean analysis: Fundamentals and practices, *Ocean Modelling*, 121: 49-75.
- Naveira Garabato, A.C., MacGilchrist, G.A et al. (2017) High latitude ocean ventilation and its role in Earth's climate transitions, *Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A*, 375: 20160324.
- MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (2017) Characterizing the chaotic nature of ocean ventilation. *Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans*, 122: 7577-7594.
- MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (2014) Effect of enhanced pCO2 levels on the production of DOC and TEP in short term bioassay experiments. *Biogeosciences*, 11: 3695-3706.

MacGilchrist, G.A. et al. (2014) The Arctic Ocean carbon sink. Deep Sea Research I, 86: 39-55.

Awards and Scholarships

Doctoral studies	Natural Environment Research Council PhD studentship	
	CASE studentship, NERC (linked to U.K. Met Office)	
	Oxford-Radcliffe-Graduate Scholar, University College	
	Sykes scholarship for travel in mainland China	
Masters studies	School fees bursary, University of Southampton	

	Educational Support Fund, Society for Underwater Technology John Raymont Fund for highest aggregate mark in MSc Oceanog	graphy	
Undergraduate studies	Excellence in 1 st three years, Newcastle University		
Invited Presentations	Individual awards for merit in 1^{st} and 2^{nd} years, Newcastle University		
Ocean ventilation in the high-latitude North Atlantic	CASPO Seminar, Scripps Institution of Oceanography (San Diego, 2018) Physical Oceanography seminar, Ifremer (Brest, 2017) Ocean Modelling Group, Challenger Society (Exeter, 2017; Liverpool, 2016)		
Characterising the chaotic nature of ocean ventilation	Ocean Sciences Meeting (Portland, 2018) MEOM Research Group seminar (Grenoble, 2017) Drakkar project meeting (Grenoble, 2017) Nanjing University Institute of Science and Technology (Nanjing Ocean University of China (Qingdao, 2016) Peking University (Beijing, 2016) Physical Oceanography and Climate seminar, NOC (Southampto Ocean Modelling Group, Challenger Society (Cambridge, 2015) Rapid-USAMOC International Science Meeting (Bristol, 2015) IUGG General Assembly (Prague, 2015) ResClim All-staff meeting (Norway, 2015)		
The Arctic Ocean carbon sink	Advances in Marine Biogeochemistry, Challenger Society (Oxfor Ocean Sciences Meeting (Hawaii, 2014) GEOMAR (Kiel, 2012) Physical Oceanography and Climate seminar, NOC (Southampto UK Polar Network Symposium (Bangor, 2012)	·	
Workshops and Summer	Schools		
•	ics Course Newfoundland, Canada atitudes in centennial to millennial scale climate variability.	2016	
	an Modelling Workshop Imperial College, London, U.K. ional workshop, organised by Erik van Sebille.	2015	
Alpine Summer School Val d'Aosta, Italy Topic: Dynamics, stochastics and predictability of the climate system.		2014	
Broad topics in fluic	inability of the Environment Cambridge, U.K. I dynamics, with focus on GFD. Iaboratory-based practical components.	2014	
Relevant employment			
Responsibilities: Op	SIS project cruise JR090, RRS James Cook peration of tethered microstructure profiler. To sample collection and salinometer measurements.	2013	
Researcher University of S Responsibilities: Pu	Southampton, U.K. blication of MSc research, further work on ocean acidification.	2012 – 2013	
	or Madagascar Cultures and Nature, Ifotaka, Madagascar ad researcher in survey of invasive plant species near Ifotaka.	2011	

Coordination of U.K. students, as part of Operation Wallacea.

Tutor and demonstrator University of Oxford, U.K.

2013 - 2017

Subjects: Vector Calculus, 3rd year undergraduate

Mathematics for Materials and Earth Science, 1st year undergraduate

Planet Earth, 1st year undergraduate

Physical Oceanography, 3rd year undergraduate

Responsibilities: Combination of small-group (2-5 students) tutorials and large-group

(20+ students) problem classes and demonstrations. Design and planning of weekly, hour-long tutorials.

Science outreach 2011-present

Regular lectures and events to a wide range of audiences, University of Oxford.

Fluid dynamics demonstrations to students and general public, University of Oxford.

 $\label{lem:condition} \textbf{Outreach talks on fluid dynamics and oceanography at Cheney School, Oxford, and}$

King's College School, London.

Society for Underwater Technology Christmas Lecture at the National Maritime Museum, Greenwich, 2013.

Tutoring with 'Science Plus Oxford', an initiative to introduce high school children to science and scientists.

Academic tutor and sports coach Future Hope, Kolkata, India

2006 & 2008

Voluntary work with disadvantaged children and young adults.

Responsibilities: Daily tutoring and sports coaching with groups of between 10 and $\,$

30 children, aged between 4 and 20.

Extra-curricular and skills

Rugby	International honours	Scotland Under 18, 19 and 20, 2005-2007		
		Under 19 World Cup in Dubai, 2006		
	Tynedale R.F.C.	Promotion to English National League 1, 2008		
		Northumberland County Cup Winner, 2008 – 2010		
	Oxford University R.F.C.	Player in Varsity Match versus Cambridge, 2013-2016		
		Two full Blues.		
I.T. Literacy	Proficient in MATLAB, Linux, Python, Fortran, R, TeX, and Microsoft Word.			
Research tools	Coding and analysing nu	Coding and analysing numerical simulations of a range of complexities.		
	Applying dynamical syste	Applying dynamical systems theory to oceanographic problems.		
	Lagrangian analysis of nu	Lagrangian analysis of numerical simulations and observations.		
	Budget calculations from	n box inversions.		
Languages	Native English speaker.			
	Good spoken French.			
Music	Cuitar trumpat siana	mandalin ukulala		
Music	Guitar, trumpet, piano, r	nandolin, ukulele.		
References				

Prof. David Marshall, PhD supervisor, University of Oxford (david.marshall@physics.ox.ac.uk)

Prof. Alberto Naveira Garabato, MSc supervisor, University of Southampton (acng@noc.soton.ac.uk)

Dr. Helen Johnson, PhD supervisor, University of Oxford (helen.johnson@earth.ox.ac.uk)

Prof. Ric Williams, PhD examiner, University of Liverpool (ric@liverpool.ac.uk)